<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>RTPProxy 3.0 Release Information</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Maksym</firstname>

      <surname>Sobolyev</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Sippy Labs</orgname>
      </affiliation>

      <email>sobomax@gmail.com</email>
    </author>

    <pubdate>21 May 2023</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2023</year>

      <holder>Maksym Sobolyev &lt;sobomax@sippysoft.com&gt;</holder>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>Welcome to RTPProxy 3.0</title>

      <para>
      We are excited to introduce RTPProxy 3.0, the latest milestone in our
      journey of refining the proxy system for Real-Time Transport Protocol
      (RTP) streams. This release marks an evolutionary leap from RTPProxy 2.2,
      released four years ago.

      Our team at Sippy Labs has rearchitected major subsystems to allow
      more parallelism, resulting in significant performance improvements.
      Our commitment to versatility has led to enhanced support for
      third-party extension modules and robust handling of both video and
      encrypted calls. Another remarkable addition is the introduction of
      a library version of RTPProxy, enabling its embedding into other
      real-time communication software.

      This document will guide you through all the new enhancements, features,
      and improvements that make RTPProxy 3.0 an industry benchmark in the
      real-time multimedia data streaming space.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Release Highlights</title>

    <section>
      <title>Major Improvements</title>

      <para>
      With RTPProxy 3.0, we are introducing a revamped architecture that
      boosts parallelism and improves overall performance significantly.
      These enhancements are a result of extensive rework of our
      processes and algorithms, leading to a more reliable, efficient, and
      powerful system. Key changes include:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Replacing the use of poll() with epoll()/kqueue() for
            less overhead doing RTP/RTCP sockets polling.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Moving RTCP handling into its own dedicated thread, freeing
            up resources and optimizing performance.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Running media generation (playback) in a separate thread,
            allowing for more streamlined operations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Eliminating a major synchronization bottleneck that
            previously hindered the command-processing thread from
            reaching its full capacity.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Upgrading the hashing algorithm for handling sessions hash
            tables to xxHash. This state-of-the-art algorithm significantly
            outperforms the previously used Pearson implementation, leading
            to faster and more efficient processing.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
      Additionally, we have worked hard to ensure compatibility and extend
      support for third-party extension modules. Notably, the new release
      comes with full support for handling video and encrypted calls,
      solidifying RTPProxy's position as a comprehensive solution for
      real-time communication needs. These improvements, along with
      numerous others, set a new standard for RTP proxy systems.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>New Features</title>

    <section>
      <title>Embedding RTPProxy</title>

      <para>
      One of the most exciting new features of RTPProxy 3.0 is the
      availability of a library version of the software. This breakthrough
      development allows for the embedding of RTPProxy into other real-time
      communication software, thereby expanding its utility and enabling a
      broader range of applications. This represents a major stride in our
      ongoing efforts to make RTPProxy as adaptable and user-friendly as
      possible.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>DTLS Gateway Module</title>

      <para>
      Another significant feature introduced in RTPProxy 3.0 is the dtls_gw
      module. This new addition allows RTPProxy to translate between encrypted
      and non-encrypted streams. More impressively, it can perform back-to-back
      re-encryption of already encrypted streams, which is particularly useful
      for secure recording purposes. This feature enhances RTPProxy's ability to
      handle encrypted calls, providing users with increased flexibility and
      security in their real-time communication needs.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Fixed Bugs</title>

    <section>
      <title/>

      <para/>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Configuration Changes</title>

    <section>
      <title/>

      <para/>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
